Anna Fariha

Kahlert School of Computing, University of Utah

♥ Warnock Engineering Building, #2851

72 Central Campus Drive, Salt Lake City, UT, 84112

afariha@cs.utah.edu afariha.github.io

L +1 801-581-3037

Research Interests

The aim of my research is to democratize data and data-driven systems towards boosting productivity and enhancing transparency. To this end, my research focuses on three key aspects of data system democratization: *enhancing usability* of data systems for both non-experts and experts, *providing explanation frameworks* to enable understanding of system behavior, and *achieving trust and fairness* in data-driven machine learning.

- Data systems usability: query by example, data summarization, discovery, wrangling, evolution.
- Metadata management and its applications: data constraints, data drift, data cleaning.
- Systems for machine learning and AI: trusted machine learning, fair machine learning, explainable AI, personalized text summarization, large language models for data wrangling.
- Causal reasoning and explanation frameworks: software debugging, automatic program repair, data debugging, explaining data non-conformance.

Education

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science

2021

Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences

University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA

- Dissertation: Enhancing Usability and Explainability of Data Systems
- Advisor: Alexandra Meliou
- Committee members: Emery Berger, Peter Haas, Suman Nath
- CGPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Master of Science in Computer Science

2020

Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences

University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA

- CGPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Master of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

2011

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Thesis: A New Approach for Frequent Human Interaction Pattern Mining in Meeting Databases
- Advisor: Suraiya Pervin
- CGPA: 4.00 out of 4.00

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

2010

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Thesis: An Algorithm for Graph Mining using Efficient Graph Indexing for Evolving Database
- Advisor: Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed
- CGPA: 3.83 out of 4.00

Employment History

University of Utah

Microsoft

7/2023 - present

Assistant Professor

Salt Lake City, UT, USA

Kahlert School of Computing

6/2021 – 5/2023 Redmond, WA, USA

Researcher
PROSE research and engineering team for AI-assisted programming

Managers: Gustavo Soares, Sumit Gulwani

Microsoft 5/2019 – 11/2019

Research Intern

Bellevue, WA, USA

PROSE research and engineering team for AI-assisted programming

Mentor: Ashish Tiwari

Project: Conformance constraints and trusted machine learning

Microsoft Research 5/2018 – 8/2018

Research Intern Redmond, WA, USA

Data Management, Exploration and Mining (DMX)

Mentor: Suman Nath

Project: Adaptive interventional debugging for finding root causes of nondeterministic software bugs

University of Massachusetts 9/2016 – 5/2021

Research Assistant Amherst, MA, USA

Data Systems Research for Exploration, Analytics, and Modeling (DREAM) Lab

Manning College of Information and Computer Sciences

Supervisor: Alexandra Meliou

Lalmatia Women's College 1/2015 – 4/2015

Guest Lecturer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Department of Business Administration

University of Dhaka 5/2014 – 8/2016

Lecturer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

United International University 5/2012 – 4/2014

Lecturer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

University of Liberal Arts 10/2011 – 1/2012

Competitive Programming Trainer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Coach for competitive programming in preparation for ACM ICPC Programming Contests

Structured Data Systems Limited 9/2011 – 5/2012

Software Engineer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Android and Blackberry mobile applications

University of Asia Pacific 10/2010 – 10/2010

Competitive Programming Trainer Dhaka, Bangladesh

Coach for competitive programming in preparation for ACM ICPC Programming Contests

Honors, Awards, & Achievements

SIGMOD Distinguished PC member	2023
SIGMOD Distinguished PC member	2022
SIGMOD Comprehensive Reproducibility Award	2022
VLDB Best Demonstration Runner-up Award	2020
Jim Gray Scholarship, CICS, UMass Amherst	2016
Special Achievement Award: Bangladesh ICT Journalist Forum	2012
Special Achievement Award: Bangladesh Bangladesh Women in IT	2012
University Scholarship for result in Bachelors of Science, U of Dhaka	2012
Special Achievement Award for outstanding performances in programming contests, U of Dhaka	2011
Dean's Honor Award (top 1%), Faculty of Engineering, U of Dhaka	2011
Dean's Award, Faculty of Engineering, U of Dhaka	2010
Fatema-Iqbal Trust Scholarship, U of Dhaka	2008
National Education Board General Scholarship (12th grade)	2006
Special Achievement Award for Higher Secondary Result, Kushtia District Council	2006
National Education Board Talent Pool Scholarship (10th grade)	2004

Best Student of the School (Kushtia Govt. Girls' High School)	2003
National Education Board Talent Pool Scholarship (8th grade)	2001
National Education Board Talent Pool Scholarship (5th grade)	1998
Travel and Accommodation Scholarships	
Invited Participant, CRA Career Mentoring Workshop, Washington, DC	2024
Invited Participant with Accommodation Support, Logic and Algebra for Query Evaluation	2023
 Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Berkeley, California 	
Invited Participant with Travel & Accommodation Support, CRA-WP Career Mentoring Workshop	2023
- Chicago, Illinois	
CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop Travel and Accommodation Award, Washington DC	2017
Programming Contests	
Rank 5, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka (Team: DU Resonance)	2011
Rank 1, Islamic University of Technology ICT Fest Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2011
Rank 1, Dhaka University National Collegiate Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2011
Rank 1, Dhaka University National Collegiate Programming Contest [Women] (Team: DU Felicity)	2011
Rank 2, SUST National Collegiate Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2010
Rank 6, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Amritapuri (Team: DU Resonance)	2010
Rank 4, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka (Team: DU Resonance)	2010
Rank 3, ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka (Team: DU Ouranos)	2009
Rank 515, Google Code Jam, (Individual, id: chorui12)	2009
Rank 4, AUST National Collegiate Programming Contest (Team: DU Resonance)	2009

Grants

Enhancing Usability and Explainability of Data Systems

Microsoft Research Dissertation Grant \$25,000 USD

Academic year 2020-2021

Training the Next Generation of Database Engineers: Responsible, User-Centric, and Efficient Data Management USHE: Computer Science Targeted Workforce Application, led by Jeff Phillips

Academic year 2023-2024

Teaching grant for developing new course: Human-centered Data Management

Publications

Journal and Conference Publications

- [1] Anjali Singh, Anna Fariha, Christopher Brooks, Gustavo Soares, Austin Henley, Ashish Tiwari, Chethan M, Heeryung Choi, and Sumit Gulwani. Investigating student mistakes in introductory data science programming. In SIGCSE 2024: The 55th ACM Technical Symposium on Computer Science Education, Portland, OR, USA, March 20-23, 2024. ACM, 2024
- [2] Rohan Bavishi, Harshit Joshi, José Cambronero, Anna Fariha, Sumit Gulwani, Vu Le, Ivan Radicek, and Ashish Tiwari. Neurosymbolic repair for low-code formula languages. *Proc. ACM Program. Lang.*, 6(OOPSLA2):1093– 1122, 2022
- [3] Sainyam Galhotra, Anna Fariha, Raoni Lourenço, Juliana Freire, Alexandra Meliou, and Divesh Srivastava. Dataprism: Exposing disconnect between data and systems. In SIGMOD '22: International Conference on Management of Data, Philadelphia, PA, USA, June 12 17, 2022, pages 217–231. ACM, 2022
- [4] Maliha Tashfia Islam, Anna Fariha, Alexandra Meliou, and Babak Salimi. Through the data management lens: Experimental analysis and evaluation of fair classification. In SIGMOD '22: International Conference on Management of Data, Philadelphia, PA, USA, June 12 17, 2022, pages 232–246. ACM, 2022

- [5] Anna Fariha, Ashish Tiwari, Arjun Radhakrishna, Sumit Gulwani, and Alexandra Meliou. Conformance constraint discovery: Measuring trust in data-driven systems. In SIGMOD '21: International Conference on Management of Data, Virtual Event, China, June 20-25, 2021, pages 499–512. ACM, 2021
- [6] Anna Fariha, Suman Nath, and Alexandra Meliou. Causality-guided adaptive interventional debugging. In *Proceedings of the 2020 International Conference on Management of Data, SIGMOD Conference 2020, online conference, June 14-19, 2020*, pages 431–446. ACM, 2020 (ACM SIGMOD Comprehensive Reproducibility Award)
- [7] Anna Fariha and Alexandra Meliou. Example-driven query intent discovery: Abductive reasoning using semantic similarity. *Proc. VLDB Endow.*, 12(11):1262–1275, 2019
- [8] Anna Fariha, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Carson K. Leung, Md. Samiullah, Suraiya Pervin, and Longbing Cao. A new framework for mining frequent interaction patterns from meeting databases. *Eng. Appl. Artif. Intell.*, 45:103–118, 2015
- [9] Amit Mandal, Mehedi Hasan, Anna Fariha, and Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed. GSCS graph stream classification with side information. In *APWeb*, pages 389–400, 2015
- [10] Md. Samiullah, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Anna Fariha, Md. Rafiqul Islam, and Nicolas Lachiche. Mining frequent correlated graphs with a new measure. *Expert Syst. Appl.*, 41(4):1847–1863, 2014
- [11] Shafaet Ashraf, Sheikh Muhammad Sarwar, Md. Abeed Hassan, Saifuddin Md. Tareeq, and Anna Fariha. An efficient method for extracting subtrees against forest query. In *Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Ubiquitous Information Management and Communication, IMCOM 2015, Bali, Indonesia, January 08 - 10, 2015*, pages 98:1–98:7. ACM, 2015
- [12] Anna Fariha, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Carson Kai-Sang Leung, S. M. Abdullah, and Longbing Cao. Mining frequent patterns from human interactions in meetings using directed acyclic graphs. In *PAKDD*, pages 38–49, 2013
- [13] Md. Samiullah, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, Manziba Akanda Nishi, Anna Fariha, S. M. Abdullah, and Md. Rafiqul Islam. Correlation mining in graph databases with a new measure. In *APWeb*, pages 88–95, 2013
- [14] Shariful Islam, Anna Fariha, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, and Byeong-Soo Jeong. EGDIM: evolving graph database indexing method. In *ICUIMC*, pages 56:1–56:10, 2012

Short, Demonstration, and Workshop Papers

- [15] Bhavya Chopra, Anna Fariha, Sumit Gulwani, Austin Z. Henley, Daniel Perelman, Mohammad Raza, Sherry Shi, Danny Simmons, and Ashish Tiwari. CoWrangler: Recommender System for Data-Wrangling Scripts. In SIGMOD '23: International Conference on Management of Data, Seattle, USA, June 18-23, 2023. ACM, 2023
- [16] El Kindi Rezig, Anshul Bhandari, Anna Fariha, Benjamin Price, Allan Vanterpool, Andrew Bowne, Lindsey McEvoy, and Vijay Gadepally. Examples are all you need: Iterative data discovery by example in data lakes. 2022
- [17] El Kindi Rezig, Anshul Bhandari, Anna Fariha, Benjamin Price, Allan Vanterpool, Vijay Gadepally, and Michael Stonebraker. DICE: data discovery by example. *PVLDB*, 14(12):2819–2822, 2021
- [18] Nishant Yadav, Matteo Brucato, Anna Fariha, Oscar Youngquist, Julian Killingback, Alexandra Meliou, and Peter Haas. SUBSUME: A dataset for subjective summary extraction from Wikipedia documents. pages 131–141, November 2021
- [19] Anna Fariha, Ashish Tiwari, Alexandra Meliou, Arjun Radhakrishna, and Sumit Gulwani. CoCo: Interactive Exploration of Conformance Constraints for Data Understanding and Data Cleaning. In SIGMOD '21: International Conference on Management of Data, Virtual Event, China, June 20-25, 2021, pages 2706–2710. ACM, 2021
- [20] Anna Fariha, Ashish Tiwari, Arjun Radhakrishna, and Sumit Gulwani. ExTuNe: Explaining Tuple Non-conformance. In *Proceedings of the 2020 International Conference on Management of Data, SIGMOD Conference 2020, online conference, June 14-19, 2020*, pages 2741–2744. ACM, 2020
- [21] Anna Fariha, Matteo Brucato, Peter J. Haas, and Alexandra Meliou. SuDocu: Summarizing Documents by Example. *Proc. VLDB Endow.*, 13(12):2861–2864, 2020 (Best Demonstration Runner Up Award)

- [22] Anna Fariha, Sheikh Muhammad Sarwar, and Alexandra Meliou. SQuID: Semantic Similarity-Aware Query Intent Discovery. In *Proceedings of the 2018 International Conference on Management of Data, SIGMOD Conference 2018, Houston, TX, USA, June 10-15, 2018*, pages 1745–1748. ACM, 2018
- [23] Quazi Marufur Rahman, Anna Fariha, Amit Mandal, Chowdhury Farhan Ahmed, and Carson K. Leung. A Sliding Window-Based Algorithm for Detecting Leaders from Social Network Action Streams. In *IEEE/WIC/ACM WI-IAT*, pages 133–136, 2015

PhD Thesis

[24] Anna Fariha. *Enhancing Usability and Explainability of Data Systems*. PhD thesis, University of Massachusetts Amherst. https://scholarworks.umass.edu/dissertations_2/2311/

Invited Talks

- Recent Trends in Scalable and Human-centric Data Systems
 - Research Challenges in Computing Seminar Series, University of Utah

October, 2023

- Through the Data Management Lens: Experimental Analysis and Evaluation of Fair Classification
 - Bias, Ethics and Trustworthiness in Data Science and AI event, University of Utah

September, 2023

- Blame the data, not the system: how data constraints can help in trustworthy machine learning and explain causes of data-system malfunction
 - Data Science Lecture Series, University of Utah

September, 2023

- University of Washington, Northwest Database Society

November, 2021

- Blame the data, not the system: How data profiles can help explain causes of data-system malfunction
 - Northwest Database Society (NWDS) Annual Meeting

May, 2023

• Enhancing usability and explainability of data systems

- DATA Lab, Northeastern University (virtual)

 Database Seminar, University of California San Diego (virtual) 	April, 2023
- Cornell University	April, 2022
 Georgia University of Technology 	April, 2022
 University of California, Santa Barbara 	March, 2022
- University of Minnesota (virtual)	March, 2022
- University of Waterloo (virtual)	March, 2022
- University of Utah	February, 2022
- University of Toronto (virtual)	February, 2022
 Pennsylvania State University (virtual) 	February, 2022
- EPIC meeting, University of California, Berkeley (virtual)	February, 2022
 Ohio State University (virtual) 	January, 2022
- CSAIL, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (virtual)	October, 2021
- Microsoft (virtual)	January, 2021
- Megagon Labs (virtual)	February, 2021
- University of Pennsylvania (virtual)	February, 2021

Teaching

· University of Utah

· University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

- CS 5353/6353 Deep Learning (undergraduate + graduate)

 Fall 2023
- CS 3960/6959 Human-Centered Data Management (undergraduate + graduate)

Spring 2024

January, 2021

 CSE 1201 - Fundamentals of Programming (undergraduate) 	Spring 2014
 CSE 1211 - Fundamentals of Programming Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2014
 CSE 1102 - Discrete Mathematics (undergraduate) 	Fall 2014
 CSE 2101 - Data Structures and Algorithms (undergraduate) 	Spring 2015
 CSE 2111 - Data Structures and Algorithms Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2015
 CSE 3113 - Microprocessor and Assembly Language Lab (undergraduate) 	Fall 2015
 CSE 1111 - Fundamentals of Computer and Computing Lab (undergraduate) 	Fall 2015
 CSE 2112 - Object Oriented Programming Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2016
 CSE 2212 - Design and Analysis of Algorithms Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2016
 CSE 4111 - Artificial Intelligence Lab (undergraduate) 	Spring 2016

• United International University, Bangladesh

- CSI 219 Discrete Mathematics (undergraduate)
- CSI 121 Structured Programming Language (undergraduate)
- CSI 122 Structured Programming Language Laboratory (undergraduate)
- CSI 228 Algorithms Laboratory (undergraduate)
- CSI 233 Theory of Computing (undergraduate)
- CSI 341 Artificial Intelligence (undergraduate)
- CSI 342 Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (undergraduate)

Student Supervision

PhD Advisor

- Shiyi He
- Whanhee Cho

Masters & Undergraduate Advisor

- · University of Utah
 - Qiaoyi Cai
- · University of Dhaka

- Quazi Marufur Rahman (MS)	2015
- Amit Mandal	2015
- Mehedi Hasan	2015
- Nitish Ranjan Bhowmik	2015
- Kazi Mazbah Uddin	2015

Mentorship

• Microsoft

- Chethan Mahadevaswamy (Predoctoral Research Fellow)	2021-2022
- Bhavya Chopra (Predoctoral Research Fellow)	2022-2023
 Yang Shi (Research Intern, PhD student at North Carolina State University) 	2022

• University of Massachusetts Amherst

- Maliha Islam (PhD) [Now at Microsoft]	2020–2021
- Hasnain Heickal (PhD)	2021–2022
- Oscar Youngquist (MS)	2021–2022
- Julian Killingback (MS)	2021
- Kanchi Masalia (MS)	2020
- Genglin Liu (Undergrad)	2020
- Lucy Cousins (Undergrad)	2019–2021
- Armand Asnani (Undergrad)	2019–2020

 Nischal Dave (Undergrad) 	2019
 Zoey (Jingyi) Sun (Undergrad from Smith College) 	2018
 Lauren Beryl Larson (REU) (Undergrad from Wellesley College) 	2017
 Michael Satanovsky (High-school Intern from Hopkins School) 	2017
Professional Services	
Panelist	
• NWDS Panel on AI+DB	2024
 NSF Information and Intelligent Systems division (IIS) 	2023
 NSF's CSGrad4US Panel: "What I wish I knew before I started graduate school", Virtual 	October, 2023
SIGMOD New Researcher Symposium, Philadelphia, USA	June, 2022
• VLDB Round Table Chair: Interactive Querying and Visualization for Large Data (virtual)	August, 2021
Program Committee	
 ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (research track) 	2021-2025
• GUIDE-AI: ACM SIGMOD Workshop on Governance, Understanding, and Integration of Data for	
Effective and Responsible AI	2024
• IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE) (demonstration track)	2024
• ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data (demonstration track)	2024
• IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE) (Ph.D. Symposium)	2023 2022–2023
 International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB) (research track) International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT) (demonstration track) 	2022–2023
 International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB) (demonstration track) 	2021–2022
Other Reviewing Service	
Reviewer of the TKDE Journal	2024
Reviewer of the VLDB Journal	2021 & 2023
• Reviewer of User Interface Software and Technology (UIST)	2021 & 2023
Session chair at International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT)	2021
• External reviewer of ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems	2021
• External reviewer of ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data	2018–2020
Problem Setter & Judge of Competitive Programming Contests	
State University Bangladesh Inter-University Programming Contest, Bangladesh	2015
SAARC Programming Contest, Bangladesh University, Bangladesh	2014
Islamic University of Technology ICT Fest, Bangladesh	2014
 SAARC Programming Contest, Bangladesh University, Bangladesh 	2013
 Bangladesh Informatics Olympiad, National Round, Bangladesh 	2013
North South University Inter-University Programming Contest, Bangladesh ACM International Callesiate Programming Contest, Phylos Bangladesh	2013
ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest, Dhaka, Bangladesh Trade vers all Control of the Control	2012
Internal Service	
Graduate Admission Committee, University of Utah	2024
• Faculty Advisor, Women in Computing at the University of Utah	2023–present
 Mentor of 1st Year PhD Student (Ishrat Jahan Eliza) Co-founder of UtahDB Research Center (URL: https://mod.cs.utah.edu) 	2023–present 2022–present
- Co-founder of Otaliob Research Center (ORL: https://mod.cs.utan.edu)	2022-present